A Guide to the Additional Papers of Hans Schmitt, 1934-2004
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of Hans Schmitt 1934-2004
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12799-e, -f, -g, -h
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These additions to the papers of Hans A. Schmitt were given to the University of Virginia Library by Hans A. Schmitt, Charlottesville, Virginia, between January 20 and March 15, 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Hans A. Schmitt was born in 1921 in Frankfurt am Main, Germany, and was raised in Frankfurt and Berlin until he was sent by his mother, Elisabeth Schmitt, who was Jewish, to a Quaker school now known as International School Eerde, The Netherlands, which he attended 1934-1937. He began college at Washington and Lee in the late 1930s, continuing with graduate study of history at the University of Chicago, where he received his A.M. at Chicago in 1943.
After becoming an American citizen, he joined the army, and served in army intelligence in Europe. Following the war he married Florence Arlene Brandow and earned his Ph.D. in 1953. His various academic jobs began at the University of Oklahoma and continued at Tulane, New York University, and the University of Virginia.
Schmitt was elected University of Virginia Professor Emeritus of History, 1991 May. He was a member of the faculty at the University of Virginia from 1971-1991. He was the author of six books; his first book The Path to European Union: From the Marshall Plan to the Common Market which won the George Louis Beer Prize from the American Historical Association.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the additional papers of Hans A. Schmitt (1921-2006), emeritus Professor of History, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia, ca. 4,158 items (9 Hollinger boxes, 4 linear shelf feet) 1934-2004.
The papers contain correspondence of the Schmitt and Hamburger families including letters to his parents, correspondence with and about Gerhard Anschütz; correspondence concerning business in Berlin; Schmitt's correspondence with publishers; correspondence with doctoral students together with files on job offers and publications; and correspondence, 1993-1997 concerning Schmitt's book Quakers and Nazis.
Also included are: a photocopy of a typescript diary by Katharina Petersen, head mistress of Quäkerschule Eerde, Eerde, Netherlands, 1934-1937; postcards and letters, 1943-1944, written from the concentration camps Konzentrationslager Herzogenbusch (a.k.a. Kamp Vught) near 's-Hertogenbosch, and Westerbork near Hooghalen by Hermann Isaac (died in Auschwitz on January 21, 1945) and Vincent [Weyand?] to Dr. Elisabeth Schmitt and Richard Schmitt, Ommen, Netherlands. A frequent correspondent of Schmitt's later correspondence is Jack Sutters of The American Friends Service Committee. Most of the correspondence in the collection written prior to World War II is in German.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by folder heading and chronologically within the folders, and grouped into three series. The first series consists of seven boxes containing materials relevant to his activities as an author and Professor of History at the University of Virginia. The second series (Box 8) contains materials relevant to the period prior to World War II, primarily consisting of family correspondence between his parents and grandparents, but also including correspondence from former students in concentration camps. The third series (Box 9) contains materials relevant to Quäkerschule Eerde (Quaker School, Eerde).
Contents List
- Series I: University of Virginia Career
  - Correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence, 1975 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence, 1980 January-August (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence, 1980 September-December (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Correspondence, 1987 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Correspondence, 1988 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Correspondence, 1989 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Correspondence, 1992 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Correspondence, including information for his book, Quakers and Nazis: Inner Light in Outer Darkness from various correspondents, 1994 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Correspondence, including information for his book, Quakers and Nazis: Inner Light in Outer Darkness from various correspondents, 1995 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Correspondence, 1996 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Correspondence, 1998 January-April (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Correspondence, 1998 May-December (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Correspondence, 1999 (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Correspondence, 2001 (Box-folder 4:1)
  - Correspondence, 2002 (Box-folder 4:2)
  - Correspondence, 2003 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Correspondence- Students- Timothy Dowling, 1986-1992 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Correspondence- Students- Robert Fuller, 1991 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Correspondence- Students- Jena Gaines, 1985-2000 (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Correspondence- Students- Michael L. Kennedy, 1976-1988 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Correspondence- Students- William McAllister, 1990-1997 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Correspondence- Students- Stephen C. MacDonald, 1973-1994 (Box-folder 4:9)
  - Correspondence- Students- Michael Ramsey, 1984-1997 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Correspondence- Students- William and Christopher Ryan, 1982-1998 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Correspondence- Students- David Slavin, 1976-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Correspondence- Students- T. Hunt Tooley, 1980-1988 (Box-folder 5:1)
  - Correspondence- Students- T. Hunt Tooley, 1989-2004 (Box-folder 5:2)
  - Correspondence- Students- Margaret Trott, 1994-1997, n.d. (Box-folder 5:3)
  - Correspondence- Students- Bruce Vandervort, 1989-1992 (Box-folder 5:4)
  - Correspondence- Students- Steven F. White, 1977-1996 (Box-folder 5:5)
  - Correspondence- Students- Robert Zaretsky, 1985-2001 (Box-folder 5:6)
  - Correspondence- Students- Martha Moore Ziegler, 1972-1991 (Box-folder 5:7)
  - Correspondence- Students- Various Graduate Students, 1964-2004 (Box-folder 5:8)
  - Diary- Trip in Spain, 1983 (Box-folder 5:9)
  - Reviews and Commentaries by Hans Schmitt, 1951-1984 (Box-folder 5:10)
  - Reviews and Commentaries by Hans Schmitt, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 5:11)
  - Reviews and Commentaries by Hans Schmitt, 1994-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 6:1)
  - Professional and Scholarly Activities, 1954-1990, n.d. (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Writings- The Democratic Movement in Germany by J. Snell (Edited and finished by H. Schmitt)- Correspondence, 1956-1971 (Box-folder 6:3)
  - Writings- The Democratic Movement in Germany by J. Snell (Edited and finished by H. Schmitt)- Correspondence and Reviews, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 6:4)
  - Writings- European Union from Hitler to de Gaulle- Correspondence, 1966-1983 (Box-folder 6:5)
  - Writings- Historians of Modern France- Correspondence and Reviews, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 6:6)
  - Writings- Lucky Victim- Correspondence in Response, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Writings- Lucky Victim- Correspondence with Publishers, 1983-1992 (Box-folder 6:8)
  - Writings- The Path to the European Union- Correspondence and Reviews, 1962-1992 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Writings- Quakers and Nazis- Correspondence in Preparation, item from 1945 is a copy, [1945], 1988-1993 (Box-folder 7:1)
  - Writings- Quakers and Nazis- Correspondence in Preparation, 1994-1995 (Box-folder 7:2)
  - Writings- Quakers and Nazis- Correspondence with Source Persons, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 7:3)
  - Writings- Quakers and Nazis- Correspondence with Source Persons, 1994 (Box-folder 7:4)
  - Writings- Quakers and Nazis- Correspondence with Source Persons, 1995-1997 (Box-folder 7:5)
  - Writings- Thesis- Gerhard Anschütz- Aus meinem Leben [Autobiography] Part I, 1936 (Box-folder 7:6)
  - Writings- Thesis- Gerhard Anschutz- Aus meinem Leben [Autobiography] Part II, 1936 (Box-folder 7:7)
  - Writings- Thesis- Gerhard Anschutz- Correspondence Concerning His Biography, 1917-1949 (Box-folder 7:8)
    A proposal by Hans A. Schmitt to write his doctoral thesis on Gerhard Anschutz, a Professor of Law and ex-Rector of the University of Heidelberg (materials chiefly in German); one letter in the folder, November 29, 1949, from Schmitt to Dr. Arnold Brecht, describes the relationship of the Schmitt family with Anschutz.
  - Writings- Thesis- Gerhard Anschutz- Printed Materials Concerning His Biography, 1919-1948 (Box-folder 7:9)
    A proposal by Hans A. Schmitt to write his doctoral thesis on Gerhard Anschutz, a Professor of Law and ex-Rector of the University of Heidelberg (materials all in German).
  - Writings- Unidentified, but concerning post World War II Europe and the European Community, n.d. (Box-folder 7:10)
- Series II: Family Correspondence and Concentration Camp Correspondence
  - Correspondence- Adolf and Jenny Hamburger, 1904-1913 (Box-folder 8:1)
  - Correspondence- Liesel (Elisabeth) Hamburger and Her Parents, Adolf and Jenny, 1914-1919 (Box-folder 8:2)
  - Correspondence- Liesel (Elisabeth) and Julius Schmitt et al., 1920-1927 (Box-folder 8:3)
  - Correspondence- Liesel (Elisabeth) and Julius Schmitt et al., 1928-1932 (Box-folder 8:4)
  - Correspondence- Concentration Camp Prisoners- Hermann Isaac, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 8:5)
  - Correspondence- Letters from Occupied Holland- Richard Hamburger, 1941-1946 (Box-folder 8:6)
  - Correspondence- Letters from Occupied Holland- Richard Hamburger, n.d. [1941- 1946] (Box-folder 8:7)
  - Correspondence- Letters from Occupied Holland- Elizabeth and Richard Schmitt, 1891, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 8:8)
  - Correspondence- Letters from Occupied Holland- Elizabeth and Richard Schmitt, 1945-1946, n.d. (Box-folder 8:9)
- Series III: Quäkerschule Eerde Material
  - Quäkerschule Eerde- Diary of a Bicycle Trip to Belgium and Diary Fragments of [Hans A. Schmitt], 1935-1938 (Box-folder 9:1)
  - Quäkerschule Eerde- Diary of a Bicycle Trip to Belgium and Diary Fragments of [Hans A. Schmitt], 1935-1938 (Box-folder 9:2)
  - Quäkerschule Eerde- Diary of the School Kept by Headmistress Katharina Petersen (2 of 2), 1935-1937 (Box-folder 9:3)
  - Quäkerschule Eerde- Photographs and Reminiscences from Reunions, 1996-1999 (Box-folder 9:4)
  - Quäkerschule Eerde- Photographs and Reminiscences from Reunions, 2000-2004 (Box-folder 9:5)
  - Quäkerschule Eerde- Report on German Liquid Fuel Supply, 1945 (Box-folder 9:6)
  - Quäkerschule Eerde- Reunion Materials, 1993-1997 (Box-folder 9:7)
  - Quäkerschule Eerde- Reunion Materials, 1998-2004 (Box-folder 9:8)
  - William Hilsley- Wohnort Emigration Exil: Ein Zeitzeuge berichtet [Autobiography of William Hildesheimer (1911-2001)], 2001